<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "journalpublishing.dtd">
<article  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="2.3" xml:lang="EN"><front ><journal-meta >
<journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">genetics</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">genetics</journal-id>
<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">genetics</journal-id>
<journal-title>Genetics</journal-title>
<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="full">Genetics</abbrev-journal-title>
<issn pub-type="ppub">0016-6731</issn>
<issn pub-type="epub">1943-2631</issn>
<publisher><publisher-name>Genetics Society of America</publisher-name></publisher>
</journal-meta><article-meta ><article-id  pub-id-type="publisher-id">GEN_198549</article-id><article-id  pub-id-type="doi">10.1534/genetics.116.198549</article-id><article-categories ><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Investigation</subject></subj-group>
</article-categories><title-group ><article-title id="article-title-1">Germ Granules Prevent Accumulation of Somatic Transcripts in the Adult <italic >Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> Germline</article-title></title-group><contrib-group id="contrib-group-1"><contrib id="contrib-1" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>Andrew Kek?pa?a</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib id="contrib-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Egelhofer</surname><given-names>Thea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="fn" rid="afn1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib id="contrib-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Rechtsteiner</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name></contrib><contrib id="contrib-4" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>Susan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="aff1">Department of Molecular, Cell and Developmental Biology, University of California, Santa Cruz, California 95064</aff></contrib-group><author-notes >
<fn id="afn1" fn-type="equal"><label>1</label><p>These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn>
<corresp id="cor1"><label>2</label>Corresponding author: Department of Molecular, Cell, and Developmental Biology, Sinsheimer Laboratories, University of California, Santa Cruz, 1156 High St., Santa Cruz, CA 95064. E-mail: <email>sstrome@ucsc.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date  pub-type="epub-ppub"><month>05</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date  pub-type="epub"><day>3</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume >206</volume><issue >1</issue><fpage >0</fpage><lpage >0</lpage><history >
<date date-type="received"><day>23</day><month>11</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>01</day><month>03</month><year>2017</year></date>
</history><permissions >
<copyright-statement>Copyright ? 2017 by the Genetics Society of America</copyright-statement>
<copyright-year>2017</copyright-year>
</permissions><self-uri  xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="GEN_198549.pdf"></self-uri><abstract >
<p>The germ cells of multicellular<!-- Q1 --> organisms prot<!-- Q2 -->ect their<!-- Q3 --> develop<!-- Q4 -->mental pot<!-- Q5 -->ential through specialized mechanisms<!-- DBComment1 --> <!-- DBComment2 --> <!-- DBComment3 --> <!-- DBComment4 --> <!-- DBComment5 -->. A shared feature of germ cells from worms to humans is the presence of nonmembrane-bound, ribonucleoprotein organelles called germ granules. Depletion of germ granules in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (<italic>i.e.</italic>, P granules) leads to sterility and, in some germlines, expression of the neuronal transgene <italic>unc-119</italic>::<italic>gfp</italic> and the muscle myosin MYO-3. Thus, P granules are hypothesized to<!-- Q6 --> maintain germ cell totipotency by preventing somatic development, although the mechanism by which P granules carry out this function is unknown<!-- DBComment6 -->. In this study, we performed transcriptome and single molecule RNA-FISH analyses of dissected P granule-depleted gonads at different developmental stages. Our results demonstrate that P granules are necessary for adult germ cells to downregulate spermatogenesis RNAs and to prevent the accumulation of numerous soma-specific RNAs. P granule-depleted gonads that express the <italic>unc-119</italic>::<italic>gfp</italic> transgene also express many other genes involved in neuronal development and concomitantly lose expression of germ cell fate markers. Finally, we show that removal of either of two critical P-granule components, PGL-1 or GLH-1, is sufficient to cause germ cells to express UNC-119::GFP and MYO-3 and to display RNA accumulation defects similar to those observed after depletion of P granules. Our data identify P granules as critical modulators of the germline transcriptome and guardians of germ cell fate.</p>
</abstract><kwd-group >
<kwd>germline</kwd><kwd><italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic></kwd><kwd>P granules</kwd><kwd>PGL-1</kwd><kwd>GLH-1</kwd><kwd>germ-soma antagonism</kwd>
</kwd-group><counts >
<fig-count count="8" />
<table-count count="0" />
<equation-count count="0" />
<ref-count count="64" />
<page-count count="0" /></counts></article-meta></front><body ><p id="paragraph-1">A cell?s fate and function are determined by its transcriptome and proteome. The transcriptomes of germ cells are unique and are comprised of RNAs that encode proteins essential for specialized, germ cell-specific functions, such as meiosis, spermatogenesis, and oogenesis (<xref id="xref-1" rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr">?Lesch and Page 2012</xref>). Throughout development, germ cells must maintain expression of germline-specific genes as well as repress genes that would lead to somatic differentiation (<xref id="xref-2" rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr">?Strome and Updike 2015</xref>). Failure to maintain appropriate gene-expression programs can lead to sterility, preventing an organism from passing its genetic information to future generations.</p><p id="paragraph-2">A conserved feature of germ cells is the presence of electron-dense, nonmembrane-bound organelles called germ granules, which include polar granules in <italic >Drosophila</italic>, chromatoid bodies in mouse spermatids, Balbiani bodies in mouse oocytes, and P granules in <italic >Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> (reviewed in <xref id="xref-3" rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">?Voronina <italic >et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). Germ granules are typically associated with the cytoplasmic face of germ cell nuclei and have been observed to overlie clusters of nuclear pores in worms, zebrafish, and mice (<xref id="xref-4" rid="bib24" ref-type="bibr">?Knaut <italic >et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref id="xref-5" rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">?Pitt <italic >et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref id="xref-6" rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr">?Chuma <italic >et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Many essential germ-granule factors are known or predicted to bind RNA. Thus, germ granules are suspected to serve as post-transcriptional processing centers to modify, degrade, and/or store messenger RNAs (mRNAs) as they exit germ cell nuclei (<xref id="xref-7" rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">?Sheth <italic >et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref id="xref-8" rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">?Updike and Strome 2010</xref>; <xref id="xref-9" rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr">?Voronina <italic >et al.</italic> 2011</xref>).</p><p id="paragraph-3">In <italic >C. elegans</italic>, P granules are maternally loaded into the one-cell embryo and then asymmetrically segregated to the germ lineage during embryogenesis (<xref id="xref-10" rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">?Updike and Strome 2010</xref>). Although segregation of the bulk of maternal P granules to the germline blastomeres is not required for germ cell specification (<xref id="xref-11" rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">?Gallo <italic >et al.</italic> 2010</xref>), P granules are required for proper germ cell development and may protect germ cells from stressful conditions such as high temperature (<xref id="xref-12" rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">?Kawasaki <italic >et al.</italic> 1998</xref>, <xref id="xref-13" rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">?2004</xref>; <xref id="xref-14" rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">?Spike <italic >et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref id="xref-15" rid="bib13" ref-type="bibr">?Gallo <italic >et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). The PGL and GLH proteins make up the core constitutive components of P granules. The three PGL proteins are worm specific. The two most important PGL proteins, PGL-1 and PGL-3, contain a predicted RNA-binding motif at their C terminus called an RGG (Arg-Gly-Gly) box (<xref id="xref-16" rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">?Kawasaki <italic >et al.</italic> 1998</xref>, <xref id="xref-17" rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">?2004</xref>). The four GLH proteins are homologs of the highly conserved Vasa protein and contain DEAD-box helicase domains, which may also bind and modulate RNAs (<xref id="xref-18" rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr">?Gruidl <italic >et al.</italic> 1996</xref>; <xref id="xref-19" rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">?Kuznicki <italic >et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref id="xref-20" rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">?Spike <italic >et al.</italic> 2008</xref>). The most important GLH protein, GLH-1, is necessary for P-granule retention at the nuclear periphery (<xref id="xref-21" rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). In addition to the PGL and GLH core components, P granules contain proteins involved in small-RNA biogenesis and the RNA interference (RNAi) pathway, suggesting that P granules are involved in small-RNA regulation in germ cells (<xref id="xref-22" rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr">?Updike and Strome 2010</xref>; <xref id="xref-23" rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">?Kasper <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><p id="paragraph-4">Recently, P granules have been implicated in maintaining germ cell fate (<xref id="xref-24" rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Germ cells that are depleted of the most important P-granule components (PGL-1, PGL-3, GLH-1, and GLH-4) sometimes express a neuron-specific transgene and a muscle-specific myosin, supporting the hypothesis that P granules prevent somatic development in the <italic >C. elegans</italic> germline. These findings raise many questions, including: (1) What is the extent of somatic development in P granule-depleted germlines? (2) Is any particular somatic fate favored over others? (3) How early do P granule-depleted germ cells start expressing somatic markers? (4) What is the mechanism by which P granules prevent expression of somatic genes in the germline?</p><p id="paragraph-5">In this study, we investigated the role of P granules in maintaining appropriate transcript accumulation patterns in the <italic >C. elegans</italic> germline. Using transcript profiling and single molecule RNA-FISH (smFISH) of dissected gonads, we show that upon depletion of P granules, major changes in mRNA levels occur in the germline. Those changes include persistence of sperm transcripts past the normal sperm-production period in hermaphrodites and progressive upregulation of transcripts from numerous genes normally expressed only in somatic cells. P granule-depleted germ cells express numerous genes involved in neuronal fate and differentiation, and those cells lose their germ cell identity, highlighting the antagonistic relationship between germ and somatic fates. Finally, we show that germlines that lack either PGL-1 or GLH-1 also misexpress somatic markers, suggesting that these factors are critical for P-granule function. Our studies show that a key role of P granules is to maintain germ cell identity, perhaps by regulating the stability and/or transcription of target mRNAs.</p><sec id="section-5e5ed3910c089cabd8ae70c00119aec8"><title id="title-af370c46fd7f7a9d04f97628f9a175ac">Materials and Methods</title><sec id="section-7cc4bd2811ec31568739104ad5c04052"><title id="title-9e7905c6d92bd0a34655245432d75ef8">Strains and worm husbandry</title><p id="paragraph-6"><italic >C. elegans</italic> strains were maintained at 15 or 20? on OP50 bacteria as described (<xref id="xref-25" rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr">?Brenner 1974</xref>). Strains used in this study include SS1174 wild type, DP132 <italic >edIs6[unc119p</italic>::<italic >unc119</italic>::<italic >gfp + </italic><ext-link id="ext-link-83d16e6e76e4b0e35e88633db3838e2e" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004397;class=Gene"><italic >rol-6</italic></ext-link><italic >] IV</italic>, SS0002 <ext-link id="ext-link-4de37dc042292267d257b0e1c768eee5" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link><italic >(ct131) </italic><ext-link id="ext-link-eaa7a1e43e9ab211243f2d757f6648ec" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene"><italic >him-3</italic></ext-link><italic >(e1147) IV</italic>, SS0804 <ext-link id="ext-link-d66b09eabb4a6544101b0e07cef74d22" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link><italic >(gk100) I/hT2(qIs48)(I;III)</italic>, SS1193 <ext-link id="ext-link-a3a789088007428b9824bdf0a34da810" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link><italic >(ok439) I/hT2(qIs48)(I;III)</italic>; <italic >edIs6[unc-119p</italic>::<italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp + </italic><ext-link id="ext-link-aa7fbeef789509a4a299f72e77526e5c" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004397;class=Gene"><italic >rol-6</italic></ext-link><italic >] IV</italic>, and SS1162 <ext-link id="ext-link-ca145cd0e23aa2b1a7edf0f8b2917351" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link><italic >(ok439) </italic><ext-link id="ext-link-f36cfcf8e166d5e2bfc881cbbbf4e90e" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link><italic >(gk225) I/hT2(qIs48)(I</italic>; <italic >III)</italic>; <italic >edIs6[unc-119p</italic>::<italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp + </italic><ext-link id="ext-link-841229a0190b603a84f6a96c2af45f98" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004397;class=Gene"><italic >rol-6</italic></ext-link><italic >] IV</italic>.</p></sec><sec id="section-ca01f731d1c22566e5f02f8692e45154"><title id="title-deb971aca08030c50af79094c50d630e">Gonad isolation and RNA extraction</title><p id="paragraph-7">For experiments using RNAi, synchronized <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> L1 worms (P0) were placed on HT115 bacteria containing empty RNAi vector (control) or expressing double-strand RNA that targets P granules (<italic >i.e.</italic>, <ext-link id="ext-link-41d50af68bcecf79074731d8e25fc5da" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-dd4120aac228a67242f5dc40ddcd1d7b" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003994;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-3</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-4aef89f490c01283568d6b9648aa91d6" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-323e3b061d990bc93716b4bb2390c7dd" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link>) or targets <ext-link id="ext-link-40a79cffd72e48a3d6549416675a9a0e" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> or <ext-link id="ext-link-5ae24ca9e0c50d6aa362b7405d3d6a88" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link>; <ext-link id="ext-link-ce8e65f15cd07b8908abfb6901096f68" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003994;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-3</italic></ext-link> (<xref id="xref-26" rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref id="xref-27" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike 2015</xref>) at 24? (day 0). Three days later, F<sub >1</sub> larvae were transferred to new control or P-granule RNAi plates and returned to 24?. The majority of these F<sub >1</sub> larvae were at the L1 or L2 stage at the time of transfer. The next day (day 4), L4 worms were visually identified by their size and the presence of a white crescent at their vulva. Gonads were dissected from L4 control worms and L4 P-granule RNAi worms and cut at the gonad bend with 301/2-gauge needles in egg buffer (pH 7.3, 27.5 mM HEPES, 130 mM NaCl, 2.2 mM MgCl<sub >2</sub>, 2.2 mM CaCl<sub >2</sub>, and 0.528 mM KCl) containing 0.5% Tween 20 and 1 mM levamisole. Sterility could not be assessed in L4 worms. However, &amp;gt;80% sterility was observed in P-granule RNAi adults that were aged from the population of worms from which L4 gonads were collected. For day 1 adults, worms were allowed to age 1 day past the L4 stage and then dissected. For day 2 adults, worms were allowed to age 2 days past the L4 stage and then dissected. In day 2 adults, gonads that visually expressed the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene were identified using a Leica MZ16F fluorescence stereomicroscope and collected as a separate sample from those that did not detectably express <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic>. For adult control gonads, gonads were dissected from fully fertile worms and cut at the gonad bend. For adult P-granule RNAi worms, gonads were collected only from sterile worms, as judged by the lack of embryos in the uterus. Large P-granule RNAi gonads were cut at the gonad bend; stunted P-granule RNAi gonads were collected in their entirety. Once dissected, gonad arms were collected in Trizol, and total RNA was extracted. For control samples, 75?100 gonads were collected per replicate. For P-granule RNAi samples, 125?150 gonads were collected per replicate. Three biological replicates were performed for each treatment and time point.</p><p id="paragraph-8">For experiments using P-granule mutants, wild type (control), <ext-link id="ext-link-caa662ee23dab1b039dd38b078205b0c" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> single mutants, or <ext-link id="ext-link-3119c4b6f4eb0e6100a90a70b6bed168" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> single mutant adults [isolated from <ext-link id="ext-link-9d168db11c2351ee6bcd61b92ecab6c1" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link><italic >(gk100)/hT2(qIs48)</italic> balanced parents] were allowed to lay eggs overnight on OP50 bacteria at 24?. The day after the egg lay, the adults were removed and the F<sub >1</sub> progeny were returned to 24? for 2 days. Day 1 adult gonads were dissected, collected into Trizol, and total RNA was extracted. Only distal gonad arms were collected from fertile wild-type worms or sterile P-granule mutant worms, as judged by the lack of embryos in the uterus. Three biological replicates were performed for the wild-type and <ext-link id="ext-link-48714d75f84b67a314676a9c67fb6d7c" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> samples, and two biological replicates were performed for the <ext-link id="ext-link-559a8e82129436246c635d7654151156" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> sample.</p></sec><sec id="section-a0aeb325c71dd4ac73265edbc750d1e3"><title id="title-2d7c2a240cac5180656160633fc3e13f">Transcript profiling and analysis</title><p id="paragraph-9">Ribosomal RNA was depleted from each RNA sample using an NEBNext rRNA Depletion Kit (Human/Mouse/Rat) (catalog number E6310), and libraries were constructed using an NEBNext Ultra RNA Library Prep Kit for Illumina sequencing (catalog number E7530). Because of the kit?s size selection steps, small RNAs could not be analyzed. Libraries were sequenced at the Vincent J. Coates Genomics Sequencing Laboratory at the University of California, Berkeley, using the Illumina HiSequation 2000, 2500, and 4000 platforms. Raw sequences were mapped to transcriptome version WS220 using TopHat2 (<xref id="xref-28" rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr">?Kim <italic >et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). Only reads with one unique mapping were allowed; otherwise default options were used. Reads mapping to ribosomal RNAs were removed from further analysis. DESeq2 (<xref id="xref-29" rid="bib32" ref-type="bibr">?Love <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>) was used for differential expression analysis. A Benjamini?Hochberg multiple hypothesis corrected <italic >P</italic>-value cutoff of 0.05 was used as a significance cutoff. Read counts for each gene were normalized using the size factor normalization function in DESeq2 to ?3.5 million reads genome wide per condition, after which replicate values were averaged. Gene ontology analysis was done using the DAVID Bioinformatics Resource version 6.7.</p></sec><sec id="section-c8fe7a6782e76069be058a7a67899cf4"><title id="title-db602668cd0d187c218d0673efa7e02a">Gene categories</title><p id="paragraph-10">Gene categories were defined using published microarray and serial analysis of gene expression (SAGE) data sets that profiled specific tissues or whole worms which contained or lacked a germline (<xref id="xref-30" rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr">?Baugh <italic >et al.</italic> 2003</xref>; <xref id="xref-31" rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">?Reinke <italic >et al.</italic> 2004</xref>; <xref id="xref-32" rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr">?Meissner <italic >et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref id="xref-33" rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr">?Wang <italic >et al.</italic> 2009</xref>), as described in <xref id="xref-34" rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr">?Rechtsteiner <italic >et al.</italic> (2010)</xref> and <xref id="xref-35" rid="bib26" ref-type="bibr">?Knutson <italic >et al.</italic> (2016)</xref>. Ubiquitous genes (1895 genes) are genes that are expressed (tag &amp;gt; 0) in all SAGE data sets that profiled germline, muscle, neuronal, and gut tissue; but that are not in the germline-enriched category. Germline-enriched genes (2230 genes) are genes with transcripts enriched in adults with a germline compared with adults lacking a germline as assessed by microarray analysis. Germline-specific genes (169 genes) are genes whose transcripts are expressed exclusively in the adult germline and accumulate in embryos strictly by maternal contribution. Sperm-specific genes (858 genes) are genes in the spermatogenesis-enriched category as described in <xref id="xref-36" rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr">?Reinke <italic >et al.</italic> (2004)</xref>, minus genes in the germline-enriched and germline-specific categories. Soma-specific genes (1181 genes) are genes expressed (tag &amp;gt; 4) in muscle, neuronal, and/or gut tissue; but not expressed (tag = 0) in germline SAGE data sets and also not in the germline-enriched category. A gene?s membership within a gene category is indicated in Supplemental Material, <ext-link id="ext-link-1" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS1.xlsx">File S1</ext-link>, with 1 denoting membership in a gene category and 0 denoting not within a gene category.</p></sec><sec id="section-fa81204084b4a1d56faf7288f6f1c7ed"><title id="title-99592724709334c1a195facfcce5f9ee">Unsupervised clustering analysis</title><p id="paragraph-11">The K-means clustering algorithm in R was used to cluster the log<sub >2</sub>-fold changes shown in Figure S3 in <ext-link id="ext-link-2" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>. A total of 14,571 genes significant in at least 1 of 10 comparisons (shown as fold-change comparisons in Figure S3 in <ext-link id="ext-link-3" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>) at an adjusted <italic >P</italic>-value of 0.05 and a log<sub >2</sub>-fold change of at least one were clustered. The number of clusters was increased until the number of clusters and their patterns stabilized but were distinct, resulting in eight clusters. Expression values in the various conditions are shown as DESeq2-normalized log<sub >10</sub> read counts; they were scaled by a factor of two, so that they would have a similar range as the fold-change values. The DESeq2 size-factor normalization scaled the samples to a total of ?3.5 million genome-wide reads per condition. Within each cluster the genes were sorted from highest to lowest average expression values across conditions, but expression values were not used to cluster the genes. Our gene set categories are also shown, red indicating the gene being part of the gene set. Box plots of DESeq2-normalized log<sub >10</sub> read counts for each gene cluster are shown across conditions in Figure S4 in <ext-link id="ext-link-4" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="section-663370e3256cfb6f1d86612469d87dad"><title id="title-6cd335ae13846f89ceecfd10c4598442">smFISH</title><p id="paragraph-12">smFISH analysis was performed on L4, day 1 adult, and day 2 adult control and P-granule RNAi gonads dissected from <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> worms as described (<xref id="xref-37" rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr">?Lee <italic >et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). Stellaris probes were designed, synthesized, and labeled by Biosearch Technologies. The <ext-link id="ext-link-29f6332346edd763cdbfa5f247d6a75e" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-a11b268a54a2e408c0c114f6cc8653f3" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link> probes were coupled to Cal Fluor Red 610; and the <ext-link id="ext-link-792c515a8a6a135d65454c51fd1eadbe" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-650413b3d82a36f49c96334c25caaa0d" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-322b2bdfcbe6c93171b79e7a479cccfa" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002245;class=Gene"><italic >lag-1</italic></ext-link> probes were coupled to TAMRA. Each probe was resuspended in 250 ?l of TE buffer, pH 8.0, and then further diluted for hybridization (<ext-link id="ext-link-06ae465e5c949cf146221adf03a959ce" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-bb3d1144395ec6515314f4865539571f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002245;class=Gene"><italic >lag-1</italic></ext-link> probes were diluted to 1:10, <ext-link id="ext-link-af45d4fea5c0f68b833657fe0f57789f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link> to 1:30, and <ext-link id="ext-link-d651c33e6aea7cea67f4176ee47ea101" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-b5d817c2fdb005a6809c6ead755ec246" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link> to 1:50). Gonads were imaged on a Solamere spinning disk confocal system controlled by ?Manager software (<xref id="xref-38" rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr">?Edelstein <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). The setup was as follows: Yokogawa CSUX-1 scan head, Nikon (Garden City, NY) TE2000-E inverted stand, Hamamatsu ImageEM ?2 camera, 561-nm laser, and Plan Apo ?60/1.4 numerical aperture oil objective. <xref id="xref-39" rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">?Figure 4</xref>, <xref id="xref-40" rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">?Figure 6E</xref>, and Figures S5 and S6B in <ext-link id="ext-link-5" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link> contain montages generated by splicing together contiguous images acquired with identical settings. Control and P-granule RNAi pairs used identical confocal settings. All images were processed with ImageJ and Adobe Illustrator.</p></sec><sec id="section-dd4b08353f47d51dab10673150ce01b3"><title id="title-6539f771168b012b079e2a76b1e07c2f">Immunocytochemistry</title><p id="paragraph-13">For antibody staining, gonads were dissected using 301/2-gauge needles in egg buffer containing 0.5% Tween 20 and 1 mM levamisole. Dissected gonads were permeabilized using the freeze-crack method, fixed for 10 min in methanol and 10 min in acetone, and stained as described (<xref id="xref-41" rid="bib56" ref-type="bibr">?Strome and Wood 1983</xref>). Antibody dilutions were 1:4000 rabbit anti-UNC-64 (<xref id="xref-42" rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">?Saifee <italic >et al.</italic> 1998</xref>), 1:1000 rabbit anti-REC-8 (<xref id="xref-43" rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr">?Liu <italic >et al.</italic> 2011</xref>), 1:500 guinea pig anti-HTP-3 (<xref id="xref-44" rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr">?MacQueen <italic >et al.</italic> 2005</xref>), 1:2000 mouse anti-GFP (Roche, catalog number 11814460001), 1:2000 rabbit anti-GFP (Novus, catalog number NB600-308), 1:2000 mouse anti-MYO-3 (<xref id="xref-45" rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr">?Priess and Thomson 1987</xref>), and 1:500 Alexa Fluor secondary antibodies (Life Technologies). Images were acquired on the Solamere spinning disk confocal system described above. <xref id="xref-46" rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">?Figure 5C</xref>, <xref id="xref-47" rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">?Figure 6, A and C</xref>, and Figure S7B in <ext-link id="ext-link-6" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link> contain montages generated by splicing together contiguous images acquired using identical settings. All images were processed with ImageJ and Adobe Illustrator.</p><p id="paragraph-14">For quantification of REC-8 or HTP-3 signal relative to UNC-119::GFP signal, three optical slices were projected for both control and P-granule RNAi gonads. Using the color histogram tool in ImageJ, the intensity of the red channel (REC-8 or HTP-3 staining) was recorded and plotted as a function of the intensity of the green channel (UNC-119::GFP) from random individual cells within the gonad. For each experiment, one control gonad and three P-granule RNAi gonads were sampled.</p></sec><sec id="section-72c91363c81f99d7f9392a0e868324e5"><title id="title-89f49aab76331c87a5013f99452833ed">Data availability</title><p id="paragraph-15">Strains and reagents are available upon request. <ext-link id="ext-link-7" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS1.xlsx">File S1</ext-link> contains processed gene expression data including fold changes and average read counts. Gene expression data are available at Gene Expression Omnibus with the accession number GSE92690.</p></sec></sec><sec id="section-283c8498811b32a8845de93242c8f931"><title id="title-3cc2c1f2cd5c6afff15a1ebfaa6c889e">Results</title><sec id="section-b9cef9235cda680f0e843096cbfdea6b"><title id="title-fefb73f7a0db41a41740d83f3a6ba13b">P-granule RNAi effectively depletes P-granule mRNAs from the germline</title><p id="paragraph-16">Depletion of P granules from the <italic >C. elegans</italic> germline causes sterility and, in some sterile worms, expression of the pan-neuronal <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene (<xref id="xref-48" rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Among UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads, ?60% also coexpressed the muscle myosin MYO-3 (<xref id="xref-49" rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). UNC-119::GFP and MYO-3 were often observed in the same regions of the germline, and those regions showed morphological changes not typical of germ cells (<italic >i.e.</italic>, loss of the rachis, loss of proper germ cell organization, and abnormal nuclear size). These features raise the possibility that depletion of P granules causes germ cells to undergo large-scale developmental changes in gene expression.</p><p id="paragraph-17">To identify genes that become misregulated upon depletion of P granules and to investigate the extent of reprogramming toward somatic cell types, we performed transcriptome analysis of dissected gonads from P granule-depleted worms compared to control worms. We treated L1 larvae that harbored the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene with P-granule RNAi and manually dissected and collected gonads from their F<sub >1</sub> progeny at different developmental stages: L4 larvae, day 1 sterile adults, and day 2 sterile adults (<xref id="xref-50" rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">?Figure 1A</xref>, see <italic >Materials and Methods</italic>). Throughout this report, we use the shorthand ?L4? to mean the L4 larval stage and ?PG(?)? to mean P-granule depleted. Of the day 2 sterile adults, ?10% expressed the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene in one or both gonad arms. These ?transformed? gonads [<italic >i.e.</italic>, day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads] were collected as a separate sample from day 2 gonads that did not detectably express the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene [<italic >i.e.</italic>, day 2 adult PG(-) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads; <xref id="xref-51" rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">?Figure 1B</xref>]. For comparison, worms were fed empty vector RNAi instead of P-granule RNAi, and control gonads were collected from fertile F<sub >1</sub> worms at the same developmental stages (L4, day 1 adult, and day 2 adult). From control worms, only the distal halves of gonads were profiled by cutting at the gonad bend so as to avoid oocytes, which are not present in PG(?) gonads. From PG(?) worms, large gonads were cut at the gonad bend and stunted gonads were collected in their entirety. Three biological replicates were collected for each treatment at each time point. Total RNA was isolated from these replicates, depleted of ribosomal RNA, and used to construct libraries for next-generation sequencing.</p><fig id="fig1" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label >Figure 1</label><caption id="caption-1"><p id="paragraph-18">Method to profile transcripts from PG(?) gonads. PG(?) is shorthand for P granule-depleted. (A) Experimental scheme and timeline to analyze the transcriptomes of control and PG(?) gonads from L4 larval, day 1 adult, and day 2 adult stages of worms grown at 24?. (B) Seven different samples were collected (three control, and four P-granule RNAi), all in triplicate. Throughout this report, the samples are color coded: control samples are in light blue, L4 and day 1 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) samples are in pink, day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) samples are in red, and day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) samples are in green.</p></caption><graphic id="graphic-1" xlink:href="gen.198549fig1"/></fig><p id="paragraph-19">Our P granule-depletion method was highly effective. Compared to control gonads, PG(?) gonads at all three developmental stages showed between a 9- and 133-fold reduction in <ext-link id="ext-link-4d0d4f27795c1bf9a8a75b662b07066b" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-af9c9a310823c2dbbf42c1a3cd81915f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003994;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-3</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-e25308d3e6ad6a6fd8b74491fdbc1bf4" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-d044ba6ac0bcaf7cc150c281758da5ed" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link> transcripts (Figure S1, A and B, in <ext-link id="ext-link-8" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>); and immunostaining of larval worms showed that PGL-1 levels were below detection in 60% of L1s (<italic >n</italic> = 131) and in 100% of L4s (<italic >n</italic> = 53 gonad arms). In addition to the four P-granule targets included in our RNAi construct, our P-granule RNAi also depleted <ext-link id="ext-link-89502da8d55df4d0ad24aea0aece9939" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001599;class=Gene"><italic >glh-2</italic></ext-link> and the DEAD-box helicase domain-containing pseudogene <italic >T08D2.3</italic>, likely due to their extensive sequence identity with <ext-link id="ext-link-36cceb41bd3cd92931524c8a90e984f9" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-73d209b524fa4e64b2f0428d612e6a96" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link>. The University of California, Santa Cruz (UCSC) genome browser tracks of these P-granule loci revealed read pileups spanning ?350 bp (Figure S1A in <ext-link id="ext-link-9" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). Based on their mapped locations, we infer that these reads originate from the RNAi construct. We also observed a fourfold increase of a portion of <ext-link id="ext-link-a880a2b3013d4e89b1ff203cdcb8d4d4" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006843;class=Gene"><italic >unc-119</italic></ext-link> transcripts in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads compared to day 2 adult control gonads (Figure S1C in <ext-link id="ext-link-10" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). The reads that mapped to <ext-link id="ext-link-ffd1b131758f71fc039bea539fb7a2f1" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006843;class=Gene"><italic >unc-119</italic></ext-link> are most likely from the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene and not the endogenous <ext-link id="ext-link-6125dc433d79da8376628ffdb8edb124" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006843;class=Gene"><italic >unc-119</italic></ext-link> locus, since only exons 2, 3, and half of 4 were upregulated and only those exons are present in the transgene. Taken together, these data show that our P granule-RNAi treatment is highly effective at depleting P-granule mRNAs and that day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads upregulate transcription of the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene.</p></sec><sec id="section-df42d61dd461e8eeca24df4957d54f77"><title id="title-b1be9573f0293e0cc1f9498f28e36e30">PG(?) adult gonads display progressive changes in transcript accumulation</title><p id="paragraph-20">We observed genome-wide changes in transcript accumulation in PG(?) adult gonads compared to control gonads. Using cut offs of an adjusted <italic >P</italic>-value of &amp;lt;0.05 and a fold change of more than twofold, we identified 2383 genes as significantly upregulated and 127 genes as significantly downregulated in day 1 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads compared to day 1 adult control gonads (<xref id="xref-52" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2A</xref>). Allowing worms to age to day 2 of adulthood resulted in 6833 genes significantly upregulated and 965 genes significantly downregulated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads compared to day 2 adult control gonads (<xref id="xref-53" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2A</xref>). Day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads showed even greater transcript accumulation changes when compared to day 2 adult control gonads: 8777 genes significantly upregulated and 3049 genes significantly downregulated (<xref id="xref-54" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2A</xref>). Comparison of the different up- and downregulated genes from each adult sample revealed high overlap but also unique genes within later gonad samples (<xref id="xref-55" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2B</xref>). The nested Venn diagrams suggest that gene misexpression in PG(?) adult gonads becomes progressively more severe over time, especially in gonads that express a somatic transgene (<xref id="xref-56" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig2" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label >Figure 2</label><caption id="caption-2"><p id="paragraph-21">Large, progressive changes in transcript accumulation are observed in adult PG(?) gonads but not in L4 larval gonads. (A) Volcano plots comparing PG(?) gonads to control gonads at different time points. Dashed lines indicate the significance cut off of <italic >q</italic> = 0.05 (horizontal line) and a twofold change in transcript level (vertical lines). The numbers of significantly misregulated genes in each quadrant are shown at the top of each plot. (B) Venn diagrams showing the overlap of genes down- or upregulated in day 1 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads (pink), day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads (red), and day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (green). The overlap of all three samples is shaded in orange. (C) PCA of all seven samples [PG(?) and control samples] across two principal components (PC1 and PC2).</p></caption><graphic id="graphic-2" xlink:href="gen.198549fig2"/></fig></sec><sec id="section-81a2c396fc870ab384adac53659435dc"><title id="title-86b16a8742e10483444f11e2bf2270fc">PG(?) L4 larval gonads display little change in transcript accumulation</title><p id="paragraph-22">In contrast to day 1 and day 2 adult PG(?) gonads, L4 PG(?) gonads showed essentially no transcript accumulation changes compared to L4 control gonads; only 9 genes were significantly downregulated and 12 genes significantly upregulated (<xref id="xref-57" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2A</xref>). Of the nine downregulated genes, five genes were direct P granule-RNAi targets (<italic >i.e.</italic>, <ext-link id="ext-link-9381a1ce17b453ba578bdb4552df88bc" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-abba462e895c087dd3efbed2a8c9cbb7" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003994;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-3</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-6489e7d071c481229fd6d352e8ab0def" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-0416e02aedbf00d15d960417b90f6290" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-00af8b009e73396f31ed74b846243f57" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001599;class=Gene"><italic >glh-2</italic></ext-link>) and two genes were likely the result of 3??5? transitive RNAi spreading (<ext-link id="ext-link-fc6399aa5722e581971f733584e6c967" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene"><italic >him-3</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-40e536c5ba4eb164be500d6d690bf16e" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001855;class=Gene"><italic >hil-4</italic></ext-link> are at the 5? ends of <ext-link id="ext-link-f6ff677d61d1f0f9fbec99993a21c824" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-3de0ee32f45740fec50633b2867f9e7d" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003994;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-3</italic></ext-link>, respectively; <xref id="xref-58" rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr">?Alder <italic >et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). Interestingly, <ext-link id="ext-link-68535c9e87194df27b8351216051a0c2" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001862;class=Gene"><italic >him-3</italic></ext-link> is transcribed in the opposite direction of <ext-link id="ext-link-29abc55dde880bdeca93fe8d4eb5674d" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link>, suggesting that transitive RNAi operates in the nucleus and can affect genes with opposite polarity from the target gene. Another gene, <italic >T12F5.2</italic>, is downregulated as a result of being in the same operon as <ext-link id="ext-link-b5bf909610a1540dae1aa6460aca4332" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link>. The 12 genes significantly upregulated in PG(?) L4 gonads did not fall into any specific gene ontology category.</p><p id="paragraph-23">Principal component analysis (PCA) of all seven samples revealed clustering of the day 1 and day 2 adult control gonad samples close to each other and far from the L4 control sample and all of the PG(?) samples along principal component 1 (PC1) (<xref id="xref-59" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2C</xref>). Surprisingly, the control L4 gonad sample is similar to all of the PG(?) samples along PC1 (<xref id="xref-60" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2C</xref>). This, along with results discussed below, suggests that gonads isolated from PG(?) adult worms are developmentally more similar to L4 gonads than adult gonads and possibly maintain mRNAs that are normally restricted to the L4 stage. These results suggest that P granules are necessary for the normal progression of germline development from the L4 stage to adult. The PG(?) samples spread out along PC2, with the day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonad sample being farthest from the others. This likely reflects differences in transcript accumulation that may underlie somatic development in transformed day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads.</p></sec><sec id="section-f13b3f77cb0f82601d2d0229d3e31e55"><title id="title-c4381ee8f65d4163b8a1acc3deb32f15">PG(?) adult gonads downregulate germline transcripts and upregulate somatic and sperm transcripts</title><p id="paragraph-24">To determine the types of genes that are misregulated in response to P-granule depletion, we analyzed the levels of mapped reads across different gene categories: ubiquitously expressed, enriched expression in the germline, expressed specifically in the germline, expressed specifically in sperm, or expressed specifically in somatic cells. These categories were defined previously using microarray and SAGE data from different tissues and from animals that possessed or lacked a germline (see <italic >Materials and Methods</italic>). After normalizing for sequencing depth across all seven samples, we compared average read counts across different gene categories.</p><p id="paragraph-25">Ubiquitous genes displayed constant levels of read counts across all seven samples (<xref id="xref-61" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3A</xref>). Closer examination of individual genes revealed a small subset of ubiquitous genes that showed upregulation in PG(?) gonads, especially in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (Figure S2A in <ext-link id="ext-link-11" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). However, for the majority of ubiquitous genes, including <ext-link id="ext-link-e955dbfd2553a0945b40a78fb6f3dd2b" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000123;class=Gene"><italic >ama-1</italic></ext-link> which encodes the large subunit of RNA polymerase II, read levels were not changed by P-granule depletion (<xref id="xref-62" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig3" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label >Figure 3</label><caption id="caption-3"><p id="paragraph-26">PG(?) gonads downregulate germline genes and upregulate sperm and somatic genes. (A) Box plots of normalized RNA-seq reads from ubiquitous genes, genes with germline-enriched expression, genes with germline-specific expression, sperm genes, and soma-specific genes in control and PG(?) gonads at different stages. Each box extends from the 25th to the 75th percentile of read values. The whiskers extending from each box indicate the 2.5th and the 97.5th percentiles. Wedges around the median indicate 95% confidence intervals for the medians. (B?E) UCSC genome browser tracks showing the abundance of RNA-seq reads from control and PG(?) gonad samples across (B) the ubiquitous gene <ext-link id="ext-link-d34943a2fb72cdf618b22ec3dcbd2ff3" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000123;class=Gene"><italic >ama-1</italic></ext-link>; (C) germline-specific genes <italic >gld-1</italic> and <italic >csr-1</italic>; (D) sperm-specific genes <italic >msp-81</italic>, <italic >-10</italic>, and <italic >-56</italic>, <italic >nspd-2</italic>, and <italic >ssp-10</italic>; and (E) soma-specific genes <ext-link id="ext-link-d51e773451f4711b09ce1b4b0fb20922" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-35e828b798cfee7b1a27bc56b6dd9729" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-634b32d874059e01bf75e1debe1b91d5" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link>. The sample names in the box plots and the genome browser tracks are abbreviated with L4 denoting L4 larvae, Ad1 denoting day 1 adults, and Ad2 denoting day 2 adults. Additionally, UNC(?) denotes no expression and UNC(+) denotes expression of the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene. The box plots and browser tracks are color coded as described for <xref id="xref-63" rid="fig1" ref-type="fig">?Figure 1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic id="graphic-3" xlink:href="gen.198549fig3"/></fig><p id="paragraph-27">Germline-enriched and germline-specific gene read counts in control gonads increased progressively from L4 larvae to day 1 adults to day 2 adults (<xref id="xref-64" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3A</xref>). Upon P-granule depletion, L4 PG(?), day 1 adult PG(?), and day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads showed levels of reads across germline genes that were similar to levels observed in L4 control gonads (<xref id="xref-65" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3A</xref>). Those levels dropped in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads compared to day 2 adult control gonads (<xref id="xref-66" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3A</xref> and Figure S2B in <ext-link id="ext-link-12" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). Examples of germline transcripts that were downregulated include transcripts encoding the P granule-associated argonaute CSR-1 and the P granule-associated translational repressor GLD-1 (<xref id="xref-67" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3C</xref>). These data suggest that P granules are required for the normal accumulation of germline transcripts and prevent the decrease in germline mRNAs in gonads that express the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene.</p><p id="paragraph-28">Sperm genes displayed elevated read counts in PG(?) adult gonads compared to control adult gonads (<xref id="xref-68" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3, A and D</xref>). In hermaphrodite worms, spermatogenesis occurs during the L4 larval stage and ends at the L4-to-adult molt, at which time oogenesis begins (<xref id="xref-69" rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr">?Hirsh <italic >et al.</italic> 1976</xref>). Consistent with this, transcripts from sperm-specific genes, such as the <italic >msp</italic> genes that encode major sperm proteins (MSPs), accumulated in L4 gonads and then abruptly declined from control adult gonads. However, these transcripts remained elevated in PG(?) adult gonads (<xref id="xref-70" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3D</xref> and Figure S2C in <ext-link id="ext-link-13" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>), supporting the suggestion from PCA analysis that P granules are necessary for germlines to progress from L4 to adulthood. These data are consistent with a recent study that also detected perdurance of sperm transcripts in P-granule RNAi day 1 adult gonads (<xref id="xref-71" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike 2015</xref>).</p><p id="paragraph-29">Soma-specific genes showed several patterns of increased transcript accumulation in PG(?) adult gonads (<xref id="xref-72" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref> and Figures S3 and S4 in <ext-link id="ext-link-14" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). Some soma-specific transcripts accumulated in a pattern resembling sperm transcripts [transcripts detected in L4 gonads, downregulated in control adult gonads, and present at elevated levels in PG(?) adult gonads], including the ?-2(IV) collagen mRNA, <ext-link id="ext-link-1a44af30343e11995e4255203b35065e" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> (<xref id="xref-73" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref>). Other transcripts, like <ext-link id="ext-link-6ac4cca1134276fe0ccf5209f4eba998" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link>, which encodes a transcription factor important in axon regeneration in neurons (<xref id="xref-74" rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr">?Yan <italic >et al.</italic> 2009</xref>); and <ext-link id="ext-link-76b6e5d357e2607d56ac879a121af69d" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link>, which encodes a Pumilio-related, RNA-binding protein that is expressed in the hypodermis and neurons (<xref id="xref-75" rid="bib36" ref-type="bibr">?Nolde <italic >et al.</italic> 2007</xref>); had very low read levels in control gonads but were significantly upregulated in PG(?) adult gonads at all stages (<xref id="xref-76" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref> and Figure S6A in <ext-link id="ext-link-15" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). In contrast to genes like <ext-link id="ext-link-873e63f75b275ced5b8f273b17a8939c" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-19f40d30eb4d90ce1efb16eccf00b8f2" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-00b410546f21a91774f95db7c369c852" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link>; some soma-specific transcripts were only significantly upregulated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads, including <ext-link id="ext-link-7933bbc817448ad670366acc946c4ff7" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link>, which encodes a membrane-bound aquaporin that is normally expressed in the excretory cell, muscle cells, motor neurons, and the hypodermis (<xref id="xref-77" rid="bib18" ref-type="bibr">?Huang <italic >et al.</italic> 2007</xref>; <xref id="xref-78" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref>). Although different somatic genes displayed different patterns of upregulation (<xref id="xref-79" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref>), as a whole, the levels of somatic gene transcripts progressively increased over time and with expression of the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene (<xref id="xref-80" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3A</xref> and Figure S2D in <ext-link id="ext-link-16" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>).</p><p id="paragraph-30">As an unbiased, genome-wide approach to determine different gene-expression patterns among our samples, we also performed K-means clustering using the fold changes of RNAs in PG(?) gonads <italic >vs.</italic> their paired controls (see <italic >Materials and Methods</italic>). The 14,571 genes that showed a significant fold change in at least one of our comparisons were grouped into eight clusters. The majority of ubiquitous genes, germline-enriched genes, and germline-specific genes grouped into cluster 1; and the majority of sperm-specific genes grouped into cluster 4 (Figures S3 and S4 in <ext-link id="ext-link-17" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). This shows that these genes act similarly within their assigned gene category; that is, the majority of germline genes show similar responses to P-granule depletion, as do the majority of sperm genes. Somatic genes were spread out among the rest of the clusters (clusters 2, 3, 5, 6, 7, and 8; Figure S3 in <ext-link id="ext-link-18" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>), supporting our observation that P-granule depletion causes several patterns of misregulation of soma-specific transcripts. Some somatic transcripts became more prevalent at progressively later stages (<italic >e.g.</italic>, <ext-link id="ext-link-1c2bd51b3a981711f3ff619e0006ec56" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> in cluster 2), while others that were detected in L4 gonads were reduced in control adult gonads, and persisted in PG(?) adult gonads (<italic >e.g</italic>., <ext-link id="ext-link-a67f2b46ca14b36315b0260ae7585146" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> in cluster 6). We suspect that the somatic genes that become highly expressed in UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (<italic >e.g.</italic>, <ext-link id="ext-link-cb68e0f4fa02be7af2d36b8e0eda673f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link> and certain genes in clusters 2, 3, and 6) are due to indirect, secondary effects of P-granule loss (see <italic >Discussion</italic>). Taken together, our transcript profiling shows that P granules are necessary to promote appropriate transcript accumulation patterns in gonads after the L4 larval stage.</p></sec><sec id="section-28dba6680e67d1708268dcb481045507"><title id="title-2032f0267b4bd8219e0b4137ef0b5649">smFISH analysis confirms that somatic transcripts accumulate in PG(?) gonads</title><p id="paragraph-31">Although our RNA-sequencing (RNA-seq) method is highly sensitive, it is unable to provide spatial information about transcript accumulation patterns within gonads. As an independent method to test if, when, and where soma-specific transcripts are upregulated in PG(?) germ cells, we performed smFISH using probes to detect several soma-specific mRNAs (<ext-link id="ext-link-ff8cdf7816dc51021c04e5d61a09fdfd" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-56e0d675df6f45025d51bcd41bba1343" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-224ee2ce774eb6d2d6af39cabc175789" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-292dfb961f2375fa334b6e2880e380a9" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link>) in control and PG(?) gonads.</p><p id="paragraph-32">By RNA-seq, <ext-link id="ext-link-7592b591b78aeee7d83ccf88512e2ad3" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts were not detected in control L4 or adult gonads but were detected in PG(?) gonads at all stages (<xref id="xref-81" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref>). By smFISH, very few <ext-link id="ext-link-865028f9871f53771b79faf1e2c59830" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts were detected in control gonads at any stage (<xref id="xref-82" rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">?Figure 4A</xref>). We did detect some <ext-link id="ext-link-ddabe7d1ad546b84b67077e474b56438" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts around the nuclei of somatic gonad cells; including the very distal tip of the gonad, likely the somatic distal tip cell; in day 1 and day 2 adult control gonads, but no signal was detected in the germline. Upon P-granule depletion, individual <ext-link id="ext-link-0707017999db4f7a0a8956458c00ee8d" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> mRNA molecules were present throughout the germ cell region of day 1 and day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads as well as day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (<xref id="xref-83" rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">?Figure 4A</xref>). Indeed, 58% of day 1 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads (<italic >n</italic> = 24) and 100% of day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (<italic >n</italic> = 13) had <ext-link id="ext-link-be754c7e4684fe1108ad94c16032b463" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts throughout the germ cell region. Unlike <ext-link id="ext-link-b817683055eff09cd104d6629f74faaa" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts, which were detected in younger PG(?) gonads by RNA-seq, <ext-link id="ext-link-901bc7132ed7445be3423767249db50f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts were only upregulated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (<xref id="xref-84" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref>). Similarly, by smFISH, <ext-link id="ext-link-916e03a7d7e7cba3f8855794f3326dc7" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts were only detected in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (<xref id="xref-85" rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">?Figure 4B</xref>), and 100% of day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads had <ext-link id="ext-link-68215e2364cecd822a389d5c92477e1f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts (<italic >n</italic> = 23). Like <ext-link id="ext-link-405e2ad03e93810eea3b3050151566c4" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts, <ext-link id="ext-link-1ba0dfbe494367f961d7d72f95d06092" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts were distributed throughout the germline and sometimes concentrated in regions around nuclei (<xref id="xref-86" rid="fig4" ref-type="fig">?Figure 4B</xref>).</p><fig id="fig4" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label >Figure 4</label><caption id="caption-4"><p id="paragraph-33">Soma-specific transcripts accumulate in PG(?) germlines. (A) smFISH analysis of <ext-link id="ext-link-0aedde0bb32cb8cc55226d56c10c8e39" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts (red) in dissected day 1 and day 2 adult control gonads, a day 1 adult PG(?) gonad, and a day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonad. (B) smFISH analysis of <ext-link id="ext-link-66600a949dff59812262798153900eb2" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts (red) in a day 2 adult control gonad and a day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonad. For each gonad in (A) and (B), UNC-119::GFP signal is in green and DAPI-stained DNA is in blue. The distal half of each gonad is shown as a z-stack projection, with the distal tip indicated by *. Boxed regions are expanded in the right-most panels. The zoomed-in regions are projections of three slices taken from the middle section of the gonad.</p></caption><graphic id="graphic-4" xlink:href="gen.198549fig4"/></fig><p id="paragraph-34">We also used smFISH to analyze <ext-link id="ext-link-3255bcd96449bccba0f72e9e0b803725" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-1fbff10380c01ae957f05487bc442603" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link> transcripts. By RNA-seq, <ext-link id="ext-link-2c1d502da5c7df5b4fed13f3b879105c" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts in control gonads behaved in a similar manner to sperm transcripts; transcripts were detected in L4 gonads and decreased in adult gonads (<xref id="xref-87" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref>). After P-granule depletion, <ext-link id="ext-link-9c6e02b5b866b138702ed633a6231005" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts persisted in adults and were especially elevated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (<xref id="xref-88" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref>). Interestingly, by smFISH, the <ext-link id="ext-link-8b6a15fce47cffd3e1bd2fc6e9ed45ff" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> signal in both L4 control and L4 PG(?) gonads mostly originated from <ext-link id="ext-link-5c8682be20da7f40972d59e06589fd40" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts concentrated in the very distal tip of the gonad, likely in the somatic distal tip cell and not in germ cells (Figure S5 in <ext-link id="ext-link-19" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). In day 2 adult control gonads, <ext-link id="ext-link-33a0bc8815d5c40806543df25d13448c" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts were mostly gone, with only a few transcripts remaining at the distal tip (Figure S5 in <ext-link id="ext-link-20" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). In contrast, in 54% (<italic >n</italic> = 36) of day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads, <ext-link id="ext-link-836eae0956fe9d622af3c759b27d9aae" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts were present throughout the gonad, frequently concentrated in regions around the nuclei of germ cells (Figure S5 in <ext-link id="ext-link-21" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). By RNA-seq, levels of <ext-link id="ext-link-ccf669101c8725ebeaa9ab2ba8bf5845" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link> transcripts were low in control gonads and elevated in both adult stages lacking P granules (Figure S6A in <ext-link id="ext-link-22" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). By smFISH, <ext-link id="ext-link-0dc4c87ef03dad7ee8cbe04b950f3880" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link> transcripts were also detected throughout the distal half of the germline in PG(?) adult gonads: 71% of day 1 adult PG(?) (<italic >n</italic> = 45) and 90% of day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) (<italic >n</italic> = 19) (Figure S6B in <ext-link id="ext-link-23" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). Very few <ext-link id="ext-link-e27b3193e3067a386de1bcf6cb62dd34" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link> transcripts were detected in the distal half of control gonads. We did detect <ext-link id="ext-link-371660abf607106fe1d9b87b7e697110" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link> transcripts in the proximal half of both control and PG(?) gonads. Taken together, our smFISH analysis corroborates our RNA-seq results and confirms that soma-specific transcripts are upregulated in PG(?) germ cells.</p><p id="paragraph-35">Our smFISH results shed light on the subset of soma-specific transcripts that are detected in L4 gonads, are reduced in control adult gonads, but persist in PG(?) adult gonads (<italic >e.g.</italic>, <ext-link id="ext-link-57357438cab1c3e9d2d087b803f2b2a9" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts in <xref id="xref-89" rid="fig3" ref-type="fig">?Figure 3E</xref>; cluster 6 in Figures S3 and S4 in <ext-link id="ext-link-24" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). Based on our RNA-seq data alone, two explanations are possible. One possibility is that these transcripts are expressed in germ cells at the L4 stage and then disappear in a P granule-dependent manner in adult gonads, similar to sperm transcripts. An alternative possibility is that these transcripts reside in the somatic gonad and appear to be downregulated in control adult gonads and upregulated in PG(?) adult gonads because of the altered ratio of somatic gonad cells to germ cells, <italic >i.e.</italic>, a lower ratio in control adults and a higher ratio in PG(?) adults with stunted germlines. Illustrating the latter possibility, our smFISH analysis detected <italic >Iet-2</italic> transcripts in the somatic gonad of L4s. However, <ext-link id="ext-link-cc6e2eabf8d4bed1031a0b237cb055e8" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002280;class=Gene"><italic >let-2</italic></ext-link> transcripts were later expressed in the germ cells of UNC-119::GFP(+) adults, along with many other somatic transcripts (<italic >e.g.</italic>, <ext-link id="ext-link-0a55174a332070a918e31889d9f856e0" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00016997;class=Gene"><italic >cebp-1</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-1476b1df78e70f843b29da33297b26f8" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00000170;class=Gene"><italic >aqp-2</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-dbad3480d76186a45bf8784e7a85055b" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004245;class=Gene"><italic >puf-9</italic></ext-link>). Thus, even somatic gonad markers can become expressed in the germlines of reprogrammed adults. Further research is needed to identify the direct <italic >vs.</italic> indirect effects that P granules have on individual genes.</p></sec><sec id="section-988bd2d7babeb603025e8d419fcd4c81"><title id="title-8c6ca151b1e5275cfbec2cef70ea05de">UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads turn on numerous genes involved in neuronal development</title><p id="paragraph-36">Most of the genes misregulated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads were also misregulated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads (<xref id="xref-90" rid="fig2" ref-type="fig">?Figure 2B</xref>). Day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads turned on many additional genes as well. Direct comparison of day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) and UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads identified 2268 genes significantly upregulated and 692 genes significantly downregulated in UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads compared to UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads (<xref id="xref-91" rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">?Figure 5A</xref>). Gene ontology analysis of the 2268 upregulated genes identified processes involved in neuron differentiation, synaptic transmission, and axon guidance, as well as a large number of genes involved in regulation of RNA metabolism (<xref id="xref-92" rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">?Figure 5B</xref>). Interestingly, we did not detect processes involved in development of other somatic cell types like hypodermis, intestine, or muscle, even though 60% of UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads also express the muscle myosin MYO-3 (<xref id="xref-93" rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>).</p><fig id="fig5" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label >Figure 5</label><caption id="caption-5"><p id="paragraph-37">Day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads upregulate genes involved in neuronal processes and downregulate genes involved in germline processes. (A) Volcano plot comparing day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads to day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads. Dashed lines indicate the significance cut off of <italic >q</italic> = 0.05 (horizontal line) and a twofold change in transcript level (vertical lines). The numbers of significantly misregulated genes in each quadrant are shown at the top of the plot. (B) Gene ontology analysis of the 2268 upregulated genes and 692 downregulated genes in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads compared to day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads. The gene ontology processes are organized based on their <italic >P</italic>-values, and the numbers of genes in each ontology category are shown in parentheses. (C) Gonads from day 2 adult control and day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119:GFP(+) worms were dissected and immunostained for UNC-64 (red), GFP (green), and DNA (blue). The distal half of each gonad is shown as a z-stack projection, with the distal tip indicated by *. Boxed regions are expanded in the right-most panels. The zoomed-in regions are projections of three slices taken from the middle section of the gonad.</p></caption><graphic id="graphic-5" xlink:href="gen.198549fig5"/></fig><p id="paragraph-38">As an independent test of whether neuronal genes other than the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene are upregulated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads, we immunostained dissected gonads for the <italic >C. elegans</italic> syntaxin homolog UNC-64. UNC-64 is a component of the core synaptic vesicle fusion machinery and is expressed throughout the nervous system (<xref id="xref-94" rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">?Ogawa <italic >et al.</italic> 1998</xref>; <xref id="xref-95" rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">?Saifee <italic >et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). In our transcriptome data, <ext-link id="ext-link-2d5f4ef73e30ca15d07c8ede81944b85" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006798;class=Gene"><italic >unc-64</italic></ext-link> transcripts were significantly upregulated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads compared to day 2 adult control and day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads. In control gonads, some UNC-64 staining was detected in the somatic sheath and distal tip cell but not in the germ cell region (<xref id="xref-96" rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">?Figure 5C</xref>). In contrast, in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads, UNC-64 staining was observed throughout the germ cell region and stained in a filamentous pattern (<xref id="xref-97" rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">?Figure 5C</xref>), which may indicate cell membranes since syntaxin is a membrane-anchored receptor (<xref id="xref-98" rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr">?Saifee <italic >et al.</italic> 1998</xref>). These data show that day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads upregulate many genes involved in neuronal development, in addition to the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene.</p></sec><sec id="section-e11af4a7e0c981bf6acdbcc0e9fa99d7"><title id="title-f42b09f4a59894181773b48d95542884">UNC-119::GFP(+) germ cells lose germline identity</title><p id="paragraph-39">Gene ontology analysis of the 692 genes downregulated in day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) <italic >vs.</italic> UNC-119::GFP(?) gonads revealed processes involved in the cell cycle, meiosis, and chromosome segregation (<xref id="xref-99" rid="fig5" ref-type="fig">?Figure 5B</xref>). Interestingly, a large number of downregulated genes were categorized as important for embryonic development, including genes whose gene products are maternally loaded into developing oocytes to support and guide early embryogenesis (<italic >e.g.</italic>, <ext-link id="ext-link-af02e6d32adee93172b16921853ee003" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003230;class=Gene"><italic >mex-5</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-97ffe012ebf7fda79f7d05305a4a5c15" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003231;class=Gene"><italic >mex-6</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-5754e08a1988c2e6e298248b79a2c8d7" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004027;class=Gene"><italic >pie-1</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-11ff55a37a048ffcf19ff24a9682c063" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003783;class=Gene"><italic >nos-1</italic></ext-link>). To test if UNC-119::GFP(+) cells lose germ cell identity upon acquisition of a neuronal fate, we stained day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads for the germline proteins REC-8 and HTP-3, and performed smFISH to detect <ext-link id="ext-link-69af058cf203e948f953ab5a854ba7e9" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002245;class=Gene"><italic >lag-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts. REC-8 is a cohesin found in the mitotic stem cell region of germlines (<xref id="xref-100" rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr">?Hansen <italic >et al.</italic> 2004</xref>), and HTP-3 is an integral component of the synaptonemal complex present in the meiotic region (<xref id="xref-101" rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr">?Severson <italic >et al.</italic> 2009</xref>; <xref id="xref-102" rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">?Figure 6, A and C</xref>). LAG-1 is a transcription factor that works downstream of Notch signaling to control germ cell entry into meiosis (<xref id="xref-103" rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr">?Crittenden <italic >et al.</italic> 2003</xref>). In day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads, we observed a mutually exclusive pattern of UNC-119::GFP and REC-8 staining; cells that expressed UNC-119::GFP lacked REC-8 and vice versa (<xref id="xref-104" rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">?Figure 6, A and B</xref>). This was also the case for HTP-3 (<xref id="xref-105" rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">?Figure 6, C and D</xref>) and <ext-link id="ext-link-7ce2dd539d05f99ffbe8c3505847a1f5" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002245;class=Gene"><italic >lag-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts (<xref id="xref-106" rid="fig6" ref-type="fig">?Figure 6E</xref>). This demonstrates the antagonistic relationship between somatic and germline fates and highlights the importance of P granules in maintaining germ cell identity.</p><fig id="fig6" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label >Figure 6</label><caption id="caption-6"><p id="paragraph-40">Acquisition of neuronal fate in PG(?) germ cells is accompanied by loss of germ cell markers. (A) Gonads from day 2 adult control and day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) worms were dissected and immunostained for REC-8 (red), GFP (green), and DNA (blue). (B) Quantification of UNC-119::GFP signal relative to REC-8 signal in germ cells from control and PG(?) gonads. (C) Same as in (A) except gonads were stained for HTP-3 (red). (D) Same as in (B) except gonads were quantified for UNC-119::GFP signal relative to HTP-3 signal. (E) smFISH analysis of <ext-link id="ext-link-fd2eb76f6b2eb670788083012736c5f9" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002245;class=Gene"><italic >lag-1</italic></ext-link> transcripts (red) in a dissected day 2 adult control gonad and a day 2 adult PG(?) UNC-119::GFP(+) gonad. For (A), (C), and (E), the distal half of each gonad is shown as a z-stack projection, with the distal tip indicated by *. Boxed regions are expanded in the right-most panels. The zoomed-in regions are projections of three slices taken from the middle section of the gonad, except for the (C) control HTP-3 gonad, which shows the top section of the gonad. In the expanded panels in (C), the red channel of the PG(?) gonad was increased to better show relative HTP-3 levels.</p></caption><graphic id="graphic-6" xlink:href="gen.198549fig6"/></fig><p id="paragraph-41">Taken together, our transcript profiling, immunostaining, and smFISH experiments demonstrate that changes to the transcriptome and proteome are occurring in at least a fraction of the germ cells in PG(?) gonads. These changes reflect both the loss of germline identity (<italic >e.g.</italic>, loss of REC-8, HTP-3, and <ext-link id="ext-link-9ed7108d306acd27e935850f7a02309a" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002245;class=Gene"><italic >lag-1</italic></ext-link> mRNA) and acquisition of somatic identity (<italic >e.g.</italic>, expression of the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene and UNC-64).</p></sec><sec id="section-d3e9f7e9a39e200b52fc168d3b6f9c48"><title id="title-b124c8ea07b475ce43a3ca5a39dad30e">The germlines from <italic >pgl-1</italic> and <italic >glh-1</italic> single mutants also express somatic markers</title><p id="paragraph-42">Our P granule-RNAi construct simultaneously targets four important P-granule genes: <ext-link id="ext-link-5d5cd669814540d2869ff0123ed7e887" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-5932d3c729a3c8ec0d29dd0adbfe3efc" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003994;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-3</italic></ext-link>, <ext-link id="ext-link-cf7a3c65693c47f1e9b9f823889f1d9c" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link>, and <ext-link id="ext-link-9c59958f83f26c8e88a0f3d12ae72c98" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link>. We tested if loss of one or two P-granule components is sufficient to cause germline expression of somatic genes by crossing the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene into <ext-link id="ext-link-122ed0b7c981ba2bdc3b1b9474f9cc89" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> single and <ext-link id="ext-link-ba3f6ddbc63d396710dece7fd42afca1" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link><italic > </italic><ext-link id="ext-link-3575c7ad7510395486e3e5c2637b22b9" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link><italic /> double mutant backgrounds and by performing single <ext-link id="ext-link-615e3ec2cbaea57fc262a5c024035226" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> RNAi or double <ext-link id="ext-link-d598286e65cf86523923e453ba64cc32" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link>; <ext-link id="ext-link-968e58aafbf74e25023d38ec4c281b47" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003994;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-3</italic></ext-link> RNAi on <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgenic worms. We detected UNC-119::GFP expression in all backgrounds tested (<xref id="xref-107" rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">?Figure 7A</xref> and Figure S7 in <ext-link id="ext-link-25" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). Additionally, of the germlines that expressed UNC-119::GFP, a fraction also expressed the muscle myosin MYO-3 (<xref id="xref-108" rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">?Figure 7A</xref> and Figure S7 in <ext-link id="ext-link-26" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>). To determine if <ext-link id="ext-link-50c09e8e87c141302c3f46fea57b64d2" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-983215e867a682b1ca86e68398f50f43" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> mutant gonads misregulate a similar set of genes, we performed transcript profiling of gonads collected from sterile day 1 adult <ext-link id="ext-link-3b95c75d9bf7ba121fd2fcfd8e3bdeb0" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> mutants and sterile day 1 adult <ext-link id="ext-link-5eb05631824f85d1cd99f4b2c51b7e58" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> mutants: neither mutant contained the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene. Comparison to wild-type gonads revealed more transcript accumulation changes in <ext-link id="ext-link-528a5eff2758e51e867a356f3c7462ca" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> mutants than in <ext-link id="ext-link-03d3885bf2c67ccee8b9a0270e509e1b" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> mutants: <ext-link id="ext-link-ab66d3d5b1804d014895299462ec2952" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> single mutants upregulated 2894 genes and downregulated 273 genes, while <ext-link id="ext-link-0069e14e7eba55f9c8115ae15d9cb74b" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> single mutants upregulated 626 genes and downregulated 110 genes (<xref id="xref-109" rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">?Figure 7B</xref>). The majority of the genes upregulated in <ext-link id="ext-link-7925d9331f17a44a391bf174f3f89197" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> gonads were also upregulated in <ext-link id="ext-link-9d2a0dcef196fa15d69cb5e42e99dac9" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> gonads (592 out of 626 genes, 94%), suggesting that PGL-1 and GLH-1 may work together to control certain transcripts (<xref id="xref-110" rid="fig7" ref-type="fig">?Figure 7C</xref>). The majority of genes upregulated in both <ext-link id="ext-link-53564855b9b0d6b0d77044e49b126394" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-180a32715bb0c14729d51f89ad3bdd3d" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> mutant gonads were also upregulated in adult P granule-RNAi gonads (Figures S3 and S4 in <ext-link id="ext-link-27" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1/FileS2.pdf">File S2</ext-link>; data not shown). These results suggest that PGL-1 and GLH-1 are both critical P-granule factors and that both are necessary to prevent somatic development within the germline.</p><fig id="fig7" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label >Figure 7</label><caption id="caption-7"><p id="paragraph-43">Germlines lacking PGL-1 or GLH-1 also misexpress somatic markers. (A) Percent of germlines expressing the neuronal marker UNC-119::GFP (green bars) in <ext-link id="ext-link-70bd011df35882cd7d1d481c6530eb96" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> single mutants, <ext-link id="ext-link-d3dd49e8ecdb4d17c1b49b472af05b9e" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link><italic > </italic><ext-link id="ext-link-3a8e241a81818f3f7572d444fec92da4" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001601;class=Gene"><italic >glh-4</italic></ext-link><italic /> double mutants, <ext-link id="ext-link-5f21f2bf570d6e987fdd4ad44cd10d71" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> single RNAi, and <ext-link id="ext-link-5a99cfb2937b0affd5cb24d2cc49c7f1" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link>; <ext-link id="ext-link-0461a9079e6e3bc6094f8e2b12397a37" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003994;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-3</italic></ext-link> double RNAi animals containing the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene. Of the germlines that expressed UNC-119::GFP, a fraction also expressed the muscle marker MYO-3 (green and red striped bars). (B) Volcano plots comparing <ext-link id="ext-link-0c76b2307000e0762c393178c3dc1f46" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> (gold) or <ext-link id="ext-link-5f1c767ab886b87c219af56d4ad4877f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> (blue) single mutant gonads to wild-type gonads. All animals lacked the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> transgene. Dashed lines indicate the significance cut off of <italic >q</italic> = 0.05 (horizontal line) and a twofold change in transcript levels (vertical lines). The numbers of significantly misregulated genes in each quadrant are shown at the top of the plot. (C) Venn diagrams showing the overlap of genes down- or upregulated in <ext-link id="ext-link-23d3b17d31829beaa06da728de80939f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00001598;class=Gene"><italic >glh-1</italic></ext-link> and <ext-link id="ext-link-1910903f17848ff3f82919d54da012d3" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00003992;class=Gene"><italic >pgl-1</italic></ext-link> single mutant gonads.</p></caption><graphic id="graphic-7" xlink:href="gen.198549fig7"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="section-a79c0b87b3adb8391f9bf100d099ad39"><title id="title-f69c52a5f8a851578a0014eeee3a23a3">Discussion</title><p id="paragraph-44">Although germ granules were first observed &amp;gt;100 years ago (<xref id="xref-111" rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr">?Ritter 1890</xref>), their functions are only starting to be understood at the molecular level. <italic >C. elegans</italic> germ granules or ?P granules? are necessary for germline development and fertility (<xref id="xref-112" rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr">?Kawasaki <italic >et al.</italic> 1998</xref>, <xref id="xref-113" rid="bib22" ref-type="bibr">?2004</xref>; <xref id="xref-114" rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr">?Spike <italic >et al.</italic> 2008</xref>) and protect the germline from expressing somatic fate markers (<xref id="xref-115" rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). In this study, we analyzed the progressive transcript changes that occur in PG(?) germlines. We treated worms with P-granule RNAi for two generations and performed transcriptome analysis of dissected gonads from the second-generation sterile hermaphrodites. In worms that lack P granules, germlines appear relatively healthy at the L4 stage but deteriorate in adults. Germline deterioration in adults is accompanied by, and perhaps caused by, aberrant persistence of sperm-specific transcripts after the sperm-production period in L4, as previously observed (<xref id="xref-116" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike 2015</xref>), and elevated levels of soma-specific transcripts. The persistence of sperm-specific transcripts into adulthood suggests that P granules promote progression of germ cells from the L4 larval stage to adulthood, and the healthy appearance and normal RNA profile of L4 germlines suggest that P granules may not be necessary for germline development during the larval stages. In adults, the majority of PG(?) germlines become reduced in size and disorganized, while a minority of germlines appear to proliferate; both categories of germlines can contain cells that have lost their previous germ cell fate and appear to be on a neuronal developmental path. Taken together, these findings reveal that <italic >C. elegans</italic> germ granules are major regulators of the germline transcriptome and prevent germ cells from undergoing somatic development, possibly by preventing the expression of somatic factors in the germline (<xref id="xref-117" rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">?Figure 8</xref>). The mechanism by which P granules perform these functions remains to be determined.</p><fig id="fig8" position="float" fig-type="figure"><label >Figure 8</label><caption id="caption-8"><p id="paragraph-45">Models of P-granule function. P granules reside over nuclear pores, where they intercept stochastically misexpressed soma-specific mRNAs (red mRNAs), while allowing germline-appropriate mRNAs (green mRNAs) to transit to the cytoplasm for translation. (Left panel) In model A, P granules prevent the translation of somatic mRNAs. (Middle panel) In model B, P granules slice somatic mRNAs into small RNAs, which in turn induce heritable silencing of somatic genes. (Right panel) In the absence of P granules, somatic mRNAs accumulate and are translated into proteins (red) that specify somatic identity and antagonize germline identity.</p></caption><graphic id="graphic-8" xlink:href="gen.198549fig8"/></fig><p id="paragraph-46">P granules reside on the outer periphery of germ cell nuclei and overlie nuclear pores (<xref id="xref-118" rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr">?Pitt <italic >et al.</italic> 2000</xref>; <xref id="xref-119" rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">?Sheth <italic >et al.</italic> 2010</xref>; <xref id="xref-120" rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2011</xref>). It has been proposed that as mRNAs exit the nucleus, P granules intercept and perhaps process these transcripts, thus influencing the transcriptome and proteome of the germline (<xref id="xref-121" rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">?Kasper <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref id="xref-122" rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">?Figure 8</xref>). Indeed, some germline transcripts have been shown to at least transiently reside in P granules (<xref id="xref-123" rid="bib49" ref-type="bibr">?Schisa <italic >et al.</italic> 2001</xref>; <xref id="xref-124" rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr">?Sheth <italic >et al.</italic> 2010</xref>). Recently, PGL-1 was shown to dimerize and to have guanosine-specific RNase activity (<xref id="xref-125" rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">?Aoki <italic >et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). This raises the possibility that PGL-1 directly influences the transcriptome by cleaving its associated mRNAs, although PGL-1?s catalytic activity is not essential for its role in fertility (<xref id="xref-126" rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr">?Aoki <italic >et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). If PGL-1 does indeed have RNase activity <italic >in vivo</italic>, then an attractive scenario is that it recognizes mRNAs inappropriate for germline development and cleaves them, while allowing germline-appropriate mRNAs to pass through P granules and be translated in the cytoplasm (<xref id="xref-127" rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">?Figure 8</xref>). Alternatively, PGL-1 and the paralogous protein PGL-3 may not have a preference for transcript type. Indeed, PGL-3 was recently shown to bind mRNA in extracts and <italic >in vitro</italic> in a sequence-independent manner (<xref id="xref-128" rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr">?Saha <italic >et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). One possibility is that P granules intercept all types of transcripts, including germline-appropriate transcripts, but effectively prevent low levels of stochastically expressed soma-specific transcripts from producing levels of proteins that would threaten germ cell identity.</p><p id="paragraph-47">Our study extends a recent analysis of transcripts from day 1 adult P granule-RNAi gonads (<xref id="xref-129" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike 2015</xref>) and documents the progressive appearance of somatic transcripts that underlies the germ-toward-soma reprogramming we previously observed in older PG(?) adults (<xref id="xref-130" rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). <xref id="xref-131" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike (2015)</xref> documented perdurance of sperm-specific transcripts in day 1 adult PG(?) gonads, as we describe in both day 1 and day 2 PG(?) adults, but they did not detect increased accumulation of soma-specific transcripts in their samples. The day 1 adult worms sampled by <xref id="xref-132" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike (2015)</xref> experienced weaker RNAi (based on RNA read counts from RNAi target genes) and contained healthier germlines than in our experiments. Thus, the defects observed by <xref id="xref-133" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike (2015)</xref> are probably the earliest defects and likely include the primary defects caused by P-granule depletion. Our stronger RNAi and additional analysis of day 2 adults with progressively reprogrammed germlines identified additional consequences, probably many secondary consequences, of P-granule depletion. Based on their observations, <xref id="xref-134" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike (2015)</xref> concluded that P granules likely repress translation of soma-specific mRNAs that are already present at low levels in the germline (<xref id="xref-135" rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">?Figure 8</xref>, model A). Our data suggest that P granules additionally affect the levels of soma-specific mRNAs in the germline, possibly by degrading soma-specific mRNAs and/or repressing transcription of soma-specific genes (<xref id="xref-136" rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">?Kasper <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref id="xref-137" rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">?Figure 8</xref>, model B).</p><p id="paragraph-48">Consistent with P granules functioning as regulators of mRNA accumulation in the germline, many RNAi factors localize to P granules, including Dicer/DCR-1, the RNA-dependent RNA polymerase EGO-1, and the argonaute proteins PRG-1 and CSR-1 (<xref id="xref-138" rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">?Batista <italic >et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref id="xref-139" rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">?Claycomb <italic >et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). PRG-1 is a Piwi-related argonaute that prevents the expression of foreign genetic elements, including transposon and transgene mRNAs. PRG-1 recognizes these mRNAs through imperfect base pairing with its associated 21U-RNAs, resulting in heritable silencing of transposon and transgene loci (<xref id="xref-140" rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">?Batista <italic >et al.</italic> 2008</xref>; <xref id="xref-141" rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr">?Ashe <italic >et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref id="xref-142" rid="bib29" ref-type="bibr">?Lee <italic >et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref id="xref-143" rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr">?Shirayama <italic >et al.</italic> 2012</xref>; <xref id="xref-144" rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr">?Bagijn <italic >et al.</italic> 2013</xref>). To maintain germline identity, PRG-1 may work with P-granule proteins to recognize and degrade soma-specific transcripts identified as ?foreign.? This information could then be relayed back into the nucleus to repress inappropriately activated, soma-specific genes through epigenetic mechanisms (<xref id="xref-145" rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">?Kasper <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref id="xref-146" rid="fig8" ref-type="fig">?Figure 8</xref>). CSR-1, another P granule-associated argonaute, recognizes its targets through associated 22G-RNAs that base pair with germline-expressed mRNAs including those important for embryogenesis (<xref id="xref-147" rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">?Claycomb <italic >et al.</italic> 2009</xref>). Interestingly, CSR-1 was recently found to tune the levels of certain germline mRNAs in a manner that is dependent on its slicer activity (<xref id="xref-148" rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr">?Gerson-Gurwitz <italic >et al.</italic> 2016</xref>). Importantly, depletion of CSR-1 and depletion of P granules cause similar transcript accumulation changes (<xref id="xref-149" rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr">?Campbell and Updike 2015</xref>), strengthening the link between argonautes and P granules in regulating the germline transcriptome.</p><p id="paragraph-49">The development of different neuronal subtypes can be induced in the <italic >C. elegans</italic> germline by simultaneous removal of certain chromatin factors and forced expression of master neuronal transcription factors (<xref id="xref-150" rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr">?Tursun <italic >et al.</italic> 2011</xref>; <xref id="xref-151" rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">?Patel <italic >et al.</italic> 2012</xref>), highlighting the plasticity of the germline. Notably, other genetic perturbations have been shown to cause <italic >C. elegans</italic> germ cells to express neuronal and muscle markers, without the need for driving transcription factors. These include loss of the H3K4 methyltransferase SET-2, loss of the nuclear argonaute HRDE-1, and concomitant loss of the NuRD complex component LET-418 and the H3K4 demethylase SPR-5 (<xref id="xref-152" rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr">?Kaser-Pebernard <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>; <xref id="xref-153" rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr">?Robert <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Because these are chromatin-based factors, they are likely to have direct effects on gene transcription. One possibility is that these factors work downstream of P granules and interpret the RNA-processing events that occur within P granules. Comparing the transcriptome of gonads lacking P granules to the transcriptomes of <ext-link id="ext-link-692410e674cf86ec13be993770d7441f" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00004782;class=Gene"><italic >set-2</italic></ext-link> or <ext-link id="ext-link-a39aceff7f60b92ddecccc23aa2407d4" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00002637;class=Gene"><italic >let-418</italic></ext-link>; <ext-link id="ext-link-d6362a0eacfae3aadb3961493b636419" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00005010;class=Gene"><italic >spr-5</italic></ext-link> mutant gonads may provide insight into how these regulatory mechanisms operate and influence each other to protect germ cell identity.</p><p id="paragraph-50">Our gene ontology analysis of genes uniquely upregulated in PG(?) gonads from day 2 adults expressing the <italic >unc-119</italic>::<italic >gfp</italic> neuronal transgene revealed processes in neuronal development. Interestingly, processes involved in muscle development and function were not observed, despite the fact that 60% of UNC-119::GFP(+) gonads also express the muscle myosin MYO-3 (<xref id="xref-154" rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr">?Updike <italic >et al.</italic> 2014</xref>). Perhaps many fewer PG(?) germ cells upregulate genes involved in muscle development than upregulate genes involved in neuronal development, which would bias our transcriptome analysis in favor of genes involved in neuron-related processes.</p><p id="paragraph-51">The expression of many neuronal genes in PG(?) day 2 adult germlines is likely to be a secondary effect of P-granule loss. The burning challenges are to identify the primary effect(s) of P-granule loss, and to determine why PG(?) germ cells appear to favor a neuronal path. One possibility is that the UNC-119::GFP transgene contributes to reprogramming PG(?) germ cells toward a neuronal fate. Although <ext-link id="ext-link-57dba0b4dde17e61df3428ec9ffe20a1" ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wormbase.org/db/get?name=WBGene00006843;class=Gene"><italic >unc-119</italic></ext-link> is conserved from worms to humans (<xref id="xref-155" rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr">?Maduro <italic >et al.</italic> 2000</xref>) and is essential for proper development of the nervous system (<xref id="xref-156" rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">?Knobel <italic >et al.</italic> 2001</xref>), its molecular function remains unknown. If endogenous UNC-119 works upstream of many neuronal genes, then perhaps even low expression of the UNC-119::GFP transgene in cells with broad developmental potential [<italic >i.e.</italic>, PG(?) germ cells] can cause these cells to acquire a neuronal identity. However, we note that the transgene encodes only the amino terminal half (the first 100 aa) of UNC-119. Another possibility is that PG(?) germ cells are reverting to a ?default? neuronal differentiation program, which has been observed in the contexts of dissociated <italic >Xenopus</italic> embryos and mammalian embryonic stem cells (ESCs) grown in culture (<xref id="xref-157" rid="bib48" ref-type="bibr">?Sato and Sargent 1989</xref>; <xref id="xref-158" rid="bib57" ref-type="bibr">?Tropepe <italic >et al.</italic> 2001</xref>). To acquire neuronal fate through this default program, ESCs must be cultured at low density and in growth factor-free conditions, suggesting an inherent propensity of ESCs to differentiate into neurons (<xref id="xref-159" rid="bib53" ref-type="bibr">?Smukler <italic >et al.</italic> 2006</xref>). Recently, the transcription factor BLIMP1 was found to be essential to reprogram human induced pluripotent stem cells (hiPSCs) into primordial germ cell (PGC)-like cells (<xref id="xref-160" rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">?Sasaki <italic >et al.</italic> 2015</xref>). Interestingly, when <xref id="xref-161" rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr">?Sasaki <italic >et al.</italic> (2015)</xref> attempted to derive PGC-like cells from <italic >BLIMP1?/?</italic> hiPSCs, essential PGC genes were not expressed and genes involved in neuronal differentiation were upregulated instead. These and our findings suggest that neuronal fate is the preferred somatic fate of cells that lose their pluripotent stem cell or germline identity. Future work should investigate if <italic >C. elegans</italic> germlines that lack P granules revert to a default neuronal program and, if so, how the neuronal program becomes activated and why it becomes activated in adults and not larval germlines.</p><p id="paragraph-52">The breadth of ribonucleoprotein complexes and the regulatory circuits they form within the <italic >C. elegans</italic> germline highlight the complex nature of this tissue. To fully understand P-granule function, a thorough analysis of individual factors like PGL-1 and GLH-1 will need to be performed, especially at the biochemical level. Additionally, identification of P granule-associated mRNAs may provide insight into how P granules prevent somatic development in the germline. Finally, because many P-granule proteins are conserved in other species, it is important to test if germ granules in other organisms including vertebrates prevent somatic development of germ cells.</p></sec><sec id="section-66a6467e3f192637fb19b8ee99825469"><title id="title-d4db47314bb0430db955ecabd5d02c5a"/></sec></body><back ><ack >
<title>Acknowledgments</title>
<p>We thank Tina Lynch and Judith Kimble for advice on single molecule RNA-FISH (smFISH) and for the <italic>lag-1</italic> smFISH probe; Mike Nonet for the UNC-64 antibody; Abby Dernburg for the REC-8 and HTP-3 antibodies; Dustin Updike for the <italic>pgl-1</italic>; <italic>pgl-3</italic> double RNA interference construct; Ben Abrams at the University of California, Santa Cruz, Life Sciences Microscopy Facility for training; and past and current members of the Strome laboratory for helpful discussions. This work used the Vincent J. Coates Genomics Sequencing Laboratory at University of California, Berkeley, supported by National Institutes of Health S10 instrumentation grants (S10 RR-029668, S10 RR-027303, and S10 OD-018174). Some strains used in this study were provided by the <italic>Caenorhabditis</italic> Genetics Center, which is funded by the National Institutes of Health Office of Research Infrastructure Programs (P40 OD-010440). This work was supported by a California Institute for Regenerative Medicine predoctoral fellowship (TG2-01157) to A.K.K. and a National Institutes of Health R01 grant (GM-34059) and an Ellison Senior Scholar in Aging Award (AG-SS-3098-12) to S.S.</p>
<p>Author contributions: A.K.K., T.E., and S.S. designed the research. A.K.K. performed the RNA sequencing (RNA-seq) and immunostaining experiments. T.E. performed the mutant analyses and smFISH experiments. A.K.K. and A.R. performed the RNA-seq bioinformatic analysis. A.K.K., T.E., and S.S. wrote the article.</p>
</ack><fn-group ><fn id="fn1"><p>Supplemental material is available online at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1">www.genetics.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1534/genetics.116.198549/-/DC1</ext-link>.</p></fn>
<fn id="fn2"><p><italic>Communicating editor: D. I. Greenstein</italic></p></fn>
</fn-group><fn-group >
<title>AUTHOR QUERIES</title>
<fn id="Q1" fn-type="other"><p>Any alternations between capitalization and/or italics in genetic nomenclature have been retained per the original manuscript. Please confirm that all genetic nomenclature has been formatted properly throughout.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q2" fn-type="other"><p>Please verify corresponding author address.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q3" fn-type="other"><p>Please verify all supplemental material links in your article.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q4" fn-type="other"><p>Please check use of italics throughout your article. GENETICS style uses italics for genes and alleles. Note that headings are set per journal style and should not be changed to italics or non-italics during proof review.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q5" fn-type="other"><p>SJS: The genus name in the article title has been expanded per the title given on the coversheet, please check.</p></fn>
<fn id="Q6" fn-type="other"><p>Please check the WormBase links throughout. A list of entities linked in this article is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="http://textpresso-dev.caltech.edu/gsa/worm/entity_link_tables/198549.html">http://textpresso-dev.caltech.edu/gsa/worm/entity_link_tables/198549.html.</ext-link></p></fn>
<fn id="Q7" fn-type="other"><p>In sentence ?Some soma-specific transcripts accumulated in a pattern resembling sperm?,? please verify if it is OK to use the Greek symbol ??? instead of the word ?alpha? in ??-2(IV) collagen.?</p></fn>
<fn id="Q8" fn-type="other"><p>Please check meaning is retained after edits to sentence ?The 14,571 genes that showed a significant fold change??</p></fn>
<fn id="Q9" fn-type="other"><p>Please check meaning is retained after edits to sentence ?Some somatic transcripts became more prevalent at progressively later??</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list id="ref-list-1"><title id="title-21">Literature Cited</title><ref id="bib1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alder</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dames</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaudet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mango</surname><given-names>S. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2003</year>?<article-title>Gene silencing in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> by transitive RNA interference.</article-title> <source>RNA</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>25</fpage>?<lpage>32</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aoki</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kershner</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bingman</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>?<article-title>PGL germ granule assembly protein is a base-specific, single-stranded RNase.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>1279</fpage>?<lpage>1284</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashe</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapetschnig</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weick</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bagijn</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>?<article-title>piRNAs can trigger a multigenerational epigenetic memory in the germline of <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>88</fpage>?<lpage>99</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bagijn</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sapetschnig</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weick</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouasker</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>?<article-title>Function, targets, and evolution of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> piRNAs.</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>337</volume>: <fpage>574</fpage>?<lpage>578</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruby</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Claycomb</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiang</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fahlgren</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2008</year>?<article-title>PRG-1 and 21U-RNAs interact to form the piRNA complex required for fertility in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Mol. Cell</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>67</fpage>?<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baugh</surname><given-names>L. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slonim</surname><given-names>D. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>E. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>C. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2003</year>?<article-title>Composition and dynamics of the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> early embryonic transcriptome.</article-title> <source>Development</source> <volume>130</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>?<lpage>900</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brenner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1974</year>?<article-title>The genetics of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Genetics</source> <volume>77</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>?<lpage>94</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Updike</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>?<article-title>CSR-1 and P granules suppress sperm-specific transcription in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> germline.</article-title> <source>Development</source> <volume>142</volume>: <fpage>1745</fpage>?<lpage>1755</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chuma</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosokawa</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanaka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakatsuji</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>?<article-title>Ultrastructural characterization of spermatogenesis and its evolutionary conservation in the germline: germinal granules in mammals.</article-title> <source>Mol. Cell. Endocrinol.</source> <volume>306</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>?<lpage>23</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Claycomb</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Batista</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pang</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vasale</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>?<article-title>The argonaute CSR-1 and its 22G-RNA cofactors are required for holocentric chromosome segregation.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>139</volume>: <fpage>123</fpage>?<lpage>134</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crittenden</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckmann</surname><given-names>C. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernstein</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wickens</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2003</year>?<article-title>Regulation of the mitosis/meiosis decision in the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> germline.</article-title> <source>Philos. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci.</source> <volume>358</volume>: <fpage>1359</fpage>?<lpage>1362</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edelstein</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsuchida</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amodaj</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pinkard</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>R. D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>?<article-title>Advanced methods of microscope control using ?Manager software.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Methods</source> <volume>1</volume>: <fpage>e10</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gallo</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Motegi</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seydoux</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>?<article-title>Cytoplasmic partitioning of P granule components is not required to specify the germline in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>330</volume>: <fpage>1685</fpage>?<lpage>1689</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gerson-Gurwitz</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sathe</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeo</surname><given-names>G. W.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2016</year>?<article-title>A small RNA-catalytic argonaute pathway tunes germline transcript levels to ensure embryonic divisions.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>165</volume>: <fpage>396</fpage>?<lpage>409</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gruidl</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuznicki</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>McCrone</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>1996</year>?<article-title>Multiple potential germ-line helicases are components of the germ-line-specific P granules of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source> <volume>93</volume>: <fpage>13837</fpage>?<lpage>13842</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hansen</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>E. J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schedl</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2004</year>?<article-title>Multi-pathway control of the proliferation <italic>vs.</italic> meiotic development decision in the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> germline.</article-title> <source>Dev. Biol.</source> <volume>268</volume>: <fpage>342</fpage>?<lpage>357</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hirsh</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Oppenheim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Klass</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1976</year>?<article-title>Development of the reproductive system of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Dev. Biol.</source> <volume>49</volume>: <fpage>200</fpage>?<lpage>219</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>C. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamitina</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agre</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strange</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>?<article-title>Functional analysis of the aquaporin gene family in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Am. J. Physiol. Cell Physiol.</source> <volume>292</volume>: <fpage>C1867</fpage>?<lpage>C1873</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaser-Pebernard</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wicky</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>?<article-title>LET-418/Mi2 and SPR-5/LSD1 cooperatively prevent somatic reprogramming of <italic>C. elegans</italic> germline stem cells.</article-title> <source>Stem Cell Rep.</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>?<lpage>559</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gardner</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinke</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>?<article-title>Homeland security in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> germ line: insights into the biogenesis and function of piRNAs.</article-title> <source>Epigenetics</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>62</fpage>?<lpage>74</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shim</surname><given-names>Y. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaminker</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>1998</year>?<article-title>PGL-1, a predicted RNA-binding component of germ granules, is essential for fertility in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>94</volume>: <fpage>635</fpage>?<lpage>645</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amiri</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fan</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dunkelbarger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2004</year>?<article-title>The PGL family proteins associate with germ granules and function redundantly in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> germline development.</article-title> <source>Genetics</source> <volume>167</volume>: <fpage>645</fpage>?<lpage>661</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pertea</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Trapnell</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pimentel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelley</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2013</year>?<article-title>TopHat2: accurate alignment of transcriptomes in the presence of insertions, deletions and gene fusions.</article-title> <source>Genome Biol.</source> <volume>14</volume>: <fpage>R36</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knaut</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pelegri</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohmann</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwarz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>N?sslein-Volhard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2000</year>?<article-title>Zebrafish vasa RNA but not its protein is a component of the germ plasm and segregates asymmetrically before germline specification.</article-title> <source>J. Cell Biol.</source> <volume>149</volume>: <fpage>875</fpage>?<lpage>888</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knobel</surname><given-names>K. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorgensen</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastiani</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2001</year>?<article-title>UNC-119 supresses axon branching in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Development</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>4079</fpage>?<lpage>4092</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rechtsteiner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>?<article-title>Reevaluation of whether a soma-to-germ-line transformation extends lifespan in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source> <volume>113</volume>: <fpage>3591</fpage>?<lpage>3596</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuznicki</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>P. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Leung-Chiu</surname><given-names>W. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Estevez</surname><given-names>A. O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2000</year>?<article-title>Combinatorial RNA interference indicates GLH-4 can compensate for GLH-1; these two P granule components are critical for fertility in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Development</source> <volume>127</volume>: <fpage>2907</fpage>?<lpage>2916</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorensen</surname><given-names>E. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>T. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimble</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2016</year>?<article-title><italic>C. elegans</italic> GLP-1/Notch activates transcription in a probability gradient across the germline stem cell pool.</article-title> <source>eLife</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e18370</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shirayama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Youngman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conte</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>?<article-title><italic>C. elegans</italic> piRNAs mediate the genome-wide surveillance of germline transcripts.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>78</fpage>?<lpage>87</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lesch</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>?<article-title>Genetics of germ cell development.</article-title> <source>Nat. Rev. Genet.</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>781</fpage>?<lpage>794</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rechtsteiner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egelhofer</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vielle</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Latorre</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2011</year>?<article-title>Broad chromosomal domains of histone modification patterns in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Genome Res.</source> <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>227</fpage>?<lpage>236</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Love</surname><given-names>M. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Anders</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>?<article-title>Moderated estimation of fold change and dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2.</article-title> <source>Genome Biol.</source> <volume>15</volume>: <fpage>550</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacQueen</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bhalla</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiser</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Villeneuve</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2005</year>?<article-title>Chromosome sites play dual roles to establish homologous synapsis during meiosis in <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>123</volume>: <fpage>1037</fpage>?<lpage>1050</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maduro</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pilgrim</surname><given-names>D. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2000</year>?<article-title>The UNC-119 family of neural proteins is functionally conserved between humans, <italic>Drosophila</italic> and <italic>C. elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>J. Neurogenet.</source> <volume>13</volume>: <fpage>191</fpage>?<lpage>212</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meissner</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dube</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorch</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>?<article-title>An integrated strategy to study muscle development and myofilament structure in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>PLoS Genet.</source> <volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e1000537</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nolde</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saka</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reinert</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Slack</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2007</year>?<article-title>The <italic>C. elegans pumilio</italic> homolog, <italic>puf-9</italic>, is required for the 3?UTR mediated repression of the <italic>let-7</italic> microRNA target gene, <italic>hbl-1</italic>.</article-title> <source>Dev. Biol.</source> <volume>305</volume>: <fpage>551</fpage>?<lpage>563</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ogawa</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harada</surname><given-names>S. I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hosono</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1998</year>?<article-title>Functional properties of the <italic>unc-64</italic> gene encoding a <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> syntaxin.</article-title> <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source> <volume>273</volume>: <fpage>2192</fpage>?<lpage>2198</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tursun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahe</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobert</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2012</year>?<article-title>Removal of Polycomb repressive complex 2 makes <italic>C. elegans</italic> germ cells susceptible to direct conversion into specific somatic cell types.</article-title> <source>Cell Rep.</source> <volume>2</volume>: <fpage>1178</fpage>?<lpage>1186</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schisa</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2000</year>?<article-title>P granules in the germ cells of <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> adults are associated with clusters of nuclear pores and contain RNA.</article-title> <source>Dev. Biol.</source> <volume>219</volume>: <fpage>315</fpage>?<lpage>333</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1987</year>?<article-title>Cellular interactions in early <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>48</volume>: <fpage>241</fpage>?<lpage>250</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rechtsteiner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ercan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Takasaki</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phippen</surname><given-names>T. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egelhofer</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2010</year>?<article-title>The histone H3K36 methyltransferase MES-4 acts epigenetically to transmit the memory of germline gene expression to progeny.</article-title> <source>PLoS Genet.</source> <volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1001091</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reinke</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gil</surname><given-names>I. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kazmer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2004</year>?<article-title>Genome-wide germline-enriched and sex-biased expression profiles in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>.</article-title> <source>Development</source> <volume>131</volume>: <fpage>311</fpage>?<lpage>323</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib43"><citation citation-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ritter</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1890</year>?<article-title>Die Entwicklung der Geschlechtsorgane und des Darmes bei Chiromomus.</article-title> <source>Zeit furr Wiss Zool Bd.</source> <volume>50</volume>: <fpage>408</fpage>?<lpage>427</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robert</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>M. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bedet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Janczarski</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Merlet</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2014</year>?<article-title>The SET-2/SET1 histone H3K4 methyltransferase maintains pluripotency in the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> germline.</article-title> <source>Cell Rep.</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>443</fpage>?<lpage>450</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nousch</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Adame-Arana</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoege</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2016</year>?<article-title>Polar positioning of phase-separated liquid compartments in cells regulated by an mRNA competition mechanism.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>166</volume>: <fpage>1572</fpage>?<lpage>1584</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saifee</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nonet</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1998</year>?<article-title>The <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans unc-64</italic> locus encodes a syntaxin that interacts genetically with synaptobrevin.</article-title> <source>Mol. Biol. Cell</source> <volume>9</volume>: <fpage>1235</fpage>?<lpage>1252</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sasaki</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokobayashi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nakamura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamoto</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yabuta</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2015</year>?<article-title>Robust in vitro induction of human germ cell fate from pluripotent stem cells.</article-title> <source>Cell Stem Cell</source> <volume>17</volume>: <fpage>178</fpage>?<lpage>194</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>S. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sargent</surname><given-names>T. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1989</year>?<article-title>Development of neural inducing capacity in dissociated <italic>Xenopus</italic> embryos.</article-title> <source>Dev. Biol.</source> <volume>134</volume>: <fpage>263</fpage>?<lpage>266</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib49"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schisa</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>J. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2001</year>?<article-title>Analysis of RNA associated with P granules in germ cells of <italic>C. elegans</italic> adults.</article-title> <source>Development</source> <volume>128</volume>: <fpage>1287</fpage>?<lpage>1298</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib50"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Severson</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ling</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>van Zuylen</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>?<article-title>The axial element protein HTP-3 promotes cohesin loading and meiotic axis assembly in <italic>C. elegans</italic> to implement the meiotic program of chromosome segregation.</article-title> <source>Genes Dev.</source> <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>1763</fpage>?<lpage>1778</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib51"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheth</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dennis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Priess</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>?<article-title>Perinuclear P granules are the principal sites of mRNA export in adult <italic>C. elegans</italic> germ cells.</article-title> <source>Development</source> <volume>137</volume>: <fpage>1305</fpage>?<lpage>1314</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib52"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirayama</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seth</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishidate</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2012</year>?<article-title>piRNAs initiate an epigenetic memory of nonself RNA in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> germline.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>150</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>?<lpage>77</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib53"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smukler</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Runciman</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Kooy</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2006</year>?<article-title>Embryonic stem cells assume a primitive neural stem cell fate in the absence of extrinsic influences.</article-title> <source>J. Cell Biol.</source> <volume>172</volume>: <fpage>79</fpage>?<lpage>90</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib54"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spike</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meyer</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Racen</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Orsborn</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirchner</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2008</year>?<article-title>Genetic analysis of the <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> GLH family of P-granule proteins.</article-title> <source>Genetics</source> <volume>178</volume>: <fpage>1973</fpage>?<lpage>1987</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib55"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Updike</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2015</year>?<article-title>Specifying and protecting germ cell fate.</article-title> <source>Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell Biol.</source> <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>406</fpage>?<lpage>416</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib56"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>1983</year>?<article-title>Generation of asymmetry and segregation of germ-line granules in early <italic>C. elegans</italic> embryos.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>15</fpage>?<lpage>25</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib57"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tropepe</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hitoshi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sirard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mak</surname><given-names>T. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossant</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2001</year>?<article-title>Direct neural fate specification from embryonic stem cells: a primitive mammalian neural stem cell stage acquired through a default mechanism.</article-title> <source>Neuron</source> <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>65</fpage>?<lpage>78</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib58"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tursun</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Patel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kratsios</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hobert</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>?<article-title>Direct conversion of <italic>C. elegans</italic> germ cells into specific neuron types.</article-title> <source>Science</source> <volume>331</volume>: <fpage>304</fpage>?<lpage>308</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib59"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Updike</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2010</year>?<article-title>P granule assembly and function in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic> germ cells.</article-title> <source>J. Androl.</source> <volume>31</volume>: <fpage>53</fpage>?<lpage>60</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib60"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Updike</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hachey</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreher</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>?<article-title>P granules extend the nuclear pore complex environment in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> germ line.</article-title> <source>J. Cell Biol.</source> <volume>192</volume>: <fpage>939</fpage>?<lpage>948</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib61"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Updike</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knutson</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Egelhofer</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strome</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2014</year>?<article-title>Germ-granule components prevent somatic development in the <italic>C. elegans</italic> germline.</article-title> <source>Curr. Biol.</source> <volume>24</volume>: <fpage>970</fpage>?<lpage>975</lpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib62"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voronina</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Seydoux</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassone-Corsi</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nagamori</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2011</year>?<article-title>RNA granules in germ cells.</article-title> <source>Cold Spring Harb. Perspect. Biol.</source> <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>a002774</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib63"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ehlers</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kohara</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>, <year>2009</year>?<article-title>Identification of genes expressed in the hermaphrodite germ line of <italic>C. elegans</italic> using SAGE.</article-title> <source>BMC Genomics</source> <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>213</fpage>.</citation></ref><ref id="bib64"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wu</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chisholm</surname><given-names>A. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group>, <year>2009</year>?<article-title>The DLK-1 kinase promotes mRNA stability and local translation in <italic>C. elegans</italic> synapses and axon regeneration.</article-title> <source>Cell</source> <volume>138</volume>: <fpage>1005</fpage>?<lpage>1018</lpage>.</citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>